DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宮飯》
We're back!
我們回來啦！
-Nothing beats the air above ground. -Here you go.
-還是地表的空氣最棒了 -來
Is it morning or evening?
現在是清晨還是黃昏？
Don't touch the window yet!
還不可以碰窗戶！
You'll disrupt the teleportation spell!
你這樣會害轉移術失敗的！
Kabru.
喀布爾
Tomorrow, I'm going to report to the Lord of the Island.
明天我會向島主報告
I want you to back up my story.
我希望你也能一起去作證
Are you going to share everything with him?
你打算一五一十全盤托出嗎？
There's no need to bring up Laios and his party specifically.
沒必要特別提到萊歐斯他們的事
I just don't want Falin to take any more lives.
我只是不希望再讓法琳殺更多的人
All right.
明白了
You should get some good rest today.
你今天就先好好休息吧
Check it out, Kuro!
你看，小黑！
Huge ship.
好大的船！
I wonder if it's packed with rich folks!
不知道上面是不是載著很多有錢人！
This is bad.
這下糟了
Toshiro,
俊朗先生
I think we should head out right now.
看來我們得立刻過去了
What's this white ship?
那艘白色的船是？
It's a ship of the western elves.
那是西方精靈的船
See that figurehead of a little bird?
你看到那個小鳥的船頭飾像了嗎？
They're known as the Canaries.
那群人被稱為金絲雀
They show up when a dungeon's danger level rises past a certain point.
迷宮的危險性超過一定程度時 那些傢伙就會出現
Their mission is to investigate dungeons and take control of them.
他們的任務是調查迷宮以及鎮壓
Word had it they were applying pressure on the Lord of the Island,
聽說他們之前就有向島主施壓
but it looks like they're really cracking down now.
看來現在準備要強行介入了
Is that even permitted?
他們被允許那樣做嗎？
This land belongs to tall-men.
這片土地是屬於長身人的吧
Short-lived races are like infants to elves and dwarves.
對精靈和矮人來說 短命的種族就如同嬰兒
And the Lord of the Island isn't skilled at negotiations.
而且島主也不太擅長交涉
We should hurry.
我們快點過去吧
Hey!
嘿！
It's you, Shuro.
修洛，你來了啊
Namari.
娜瑪莉
Where's Falin?
法琳呢？
Laios and the others haven't given up yet, though.
萊歐斯他們似乎還沒放棄
I see.
這樣啊
Were they eating "you know what"?
他們有吃“那個”嗎？
They were.
有吃
We've come to see the Lord of the Island.
我們是來見島主的
That's not possible.
你們見不到他的
Some important folks showed up suddenly, and he's been in there since.
他突然說有重要人物來訪 之後就一直在裡面
It's been hours now.
已經窩好幾個小時了
We're too late.
看來我們來遲了
Let's go inside.
我們進去吧
We can't do that.
那樣不太好吧
If the elves get hold of the dungeon, it's going to be over.
若迷宮被交給精靈就完蛋了
My hometown also thrived because of a dungeon.
我的故鄉也曾因迷宮而繁榮昌盛
But one day, monsters flooded out,
但某一天魔物突然大量湧出
the elves came, and many lost their lives.
後來精靈來了，死了很多人
Why did my family have to die?
為何我的家人非死不可？
My mother worked so hard to raise me on her own.
我的母親含辛茹苦獨自把我養大
She didn't deserve to die like that.
她不應該以那種方式死去
I don't want to see that happen again.
我不希望再看到同樣的事重演
The existing system, where only certain races wield power,
現今這種權力集中在 特定人種上的結構
is detrimental to everyone involved.
對所有人來說都是有害的
Excuse us.
打擾了
We've come to make a report to the Lord of the Island.
我們有事想向島主大人報告 因此前來此地
What is it?
什麼事？
As you can see, we're in the middle of a discussion.
如你所見，我們有要事得討論
We ask you to leave.
請你出去吧
It concerns the current condition of the dungeon.
我想報告迷宮的現狀
Please hear us out.
請聽一下
I mustn't be intimidated.
我不可以被他們的氣勢所壓倒
Keep it brief.
那就簡短報告吧
Just earlier, while exploring the dungeon,
我們在先前探索迷宮時
we encountered a human who had been transformed into a monster.
遭遇變身成魔物的人類
-What?
-什麼？
Dammit. A Chimera.
可惡，是奇美拉
It's advancing quicker than we thought.
比我們料想的還要快
See? What did I tell you?
你看，我就說吧
I knew we couldn't afford to leisurely wait for a response!
根本沒時間悠哉地等候回覆！
Order them to come ashore at once!
現在立刻命令他們上岸！
You have no right to do that!
你怎麼可以擅自決定！
Calm down, old man.
這位老者，你冷靜一下
Borders become inconsequential when lives are at stake.
跟人命比起來 國境不過是微不足道的小事
You have no right to treat me as elderly!
還輪不到你們來把我當成老人！
Tansu, why don't we let them have their way?
坦斯，差不多夠了吧？
What?
什麼？
I'm impressed, my lord.
不愧是島主大人
You are flexible and wise.
想法靈活又聰明
Please place your seal here.
請在這裡蓋章
You mustn't! You can't!
萬萬不可！千萬不行啊！
That just made matters worse.
反而讓事態惡化了
If only…
其實…
I had the ability to take control of the dungeon,
如果我的實力足以壓制迷宮
there wouldn't be an issue.
這一切都不成問題
But it was beyond me.
但那是不可能的
So I began searching for ways to assist other capable adventurers.
所以我才開始調查 是否能支援其他有實力的冒險者
But the majority of them turned out to be self-centered and insignificant.
結果發現大多數的人都很利己 實力也不怎麼樣
Just as I resolved to tackle the dungeon myself,
當我下定決心要自行攻掠迷宮時
I heard rumors about the Touden siblings.
我聽到了關於托登兄妹的傳聞
He must come from good stock.
他看來是好人家的孩子
He's got good instincts, but he's just too selfless.
雖然直覺靈敏，但清心寡慾
Anyway, he's weird.
總之是個奇怪的傢伙
The more I looked into him, the stranger he seemed.
越是深入探究他，越覺得他奇異
He's not particularly strong, yet he somehow made it to the lower levels.
實力也不是特別強大 卻能到達迷宮深層
Giving money to folks with nothing but bad gossip surrounding them.
把錢給風評一直很差的一行人
His mysterious background.
充滿謎團的出身
His odd companions.
無法理解的奇特人際關係
But for some reason, I had a hunch that this man
但不知為何，我的直覺告訴我
might play a big part in the fate of this island.
這個男人應該 和這座島的命運緊密相依
The question is whether it'll be for better or worse.
問題是這究竟是好是壞
I've been eager to talk with him in person and form my own opinion.
我一直想和他本人談話後再下判斷
And after finally conversing with him, I've become convinced.
終於見到他，實際聊過之後 我可以確信一件事
All he cares about are monsters.
他的腦中只有魔物而已
He's incapable of considering the future of the island.
那傢伙既無法思考島嶼的未來
It shouldn't be left in his hands, but I'm sure of one thing.
也不能將島託付給他 但我能肯定這件事
Currently,
在現階段
among all the tall-men, he's the closest to reaching the heart of the dungeon.
他是長身人中最接近迷宮核心的人
This could be his one and only chance.
這恐怕是最初也是最後的機會
Therefore, I can't let the elves interfere.
可不能讓精靈來壞事
Dealing with him must wait until later.
關於要怎麼處置那傢伙 可以等之後再說
I've had enough of this.
夠了啦
Do as you please.
就隨你們的意吧
My lord!
島主大人！
Give the order to come ashore.
那就命令他們上岸吧
Please wait!
請等一下！
The dungeon's layout, environment, and the types of monsters within
目前迷宮的結構、環境
are undergoing drastic changes.
以及魔物種類的變化都相當激烈
It's extremely unstable.
相當不穩定
We're well aware of that.
這我們當然知道
It's a natural occurrence during a dungeon's expansion.
這是迷宮成長時的特徵
We must halt it without any delay.
必須盡快阻止才行
It's similar to a person's growth spurt,
就像人類的成長期
a phase that requires the most nourishment.
是最需要營養的時候
What're you talking about?
你在說什麼啊？
Fifteen years ago, my hometown
我的故鄉在15年前
was destroyed because of a dungeon.
因迷宮而滅亡
It was a town called Utaya.
那座城鎮叫烏塔亞
Fifteen years ago?
15年前？
That means…
所以說…
Are you the kid who survived that incident?
你就是那個當年倖存的孩子嗎？
I heard that the vice commander at the time took you in.
記得我之前聽過 是當時的副隊長把你帶回去的
That's right.
對
I was in her care for a few years.
她照顧了我幾年
Hmm.
這樣啊
She must've doted on you, and yet you became an adventurer.
她那麼疼愛你，結果你卻成了冒險者
I dreamt of enlisting, but the racial barrier stood in my way.
我曾夢想著入隊 但人種的鴻溝實在太大
But I wanted to do what I could
但我希望能夠盡一己之力
to prevent another tragedy like the one in my hometown.
避免讓故鄉的悲劇再次重演
How admirable.
真令人感佩呢
Are you making enough to eat?
你現在有好好養活自己嗎？
You should visit her and show her how you're doing once in a while.
偶爾也回去露個面，讓她安心吧
And?
所以呢？
You mentioned nourishment.
你剛才提到的“營養”
What about it?
是什麼意思？
Continue.
繼續說下去
Thanks to your efforts,
多虧有你們的努力
the dungeon in Utaya collapsed swiftly.
烏塔亞的迷宮不久後便倒塌了
But many soldiers and citizens lost their lives.
但也因此死了許多士兵及居民
Because the dead turned into monsters
這是由於死者化為魔物後
and ate people alive.
將活人吞噬的緣故
I heard there were many soldiers who were ambushed from behind.
據說也有很多士兵從背後遭到襲擊
Even if you charge in with sheer numbers, it will be like Utaya all over again.
就算用人海戰術進攻 也只會重蹈覆轍，變成下一個烏塔亞
I propose sealing the dungeon.
我提議封鎖迷宮
We must not feed it.
我們不可以餵養迷宮
Damaging the dungeon through combat can't be what you want either.
各位也不希望迷宮因戰鬥而毀損吧
What about the people still inside?
還留在裡面的人類怎麼辦？
Most of them are on the first level.
他們大多數都集中在第一層
We'll evacuate them gradually.
我們可讓他們逐步撤出
Everyone has some connections.
大家都有自己的交流管道
I know people I can reach out to for assistance.
我也認識幾個可以協助我們的人
Please let me handle this!
請交給我來處理！
This guy
這個小子
ate monsters with a background like that?
有著那樣的過去居然還吃了魔物？
Hey, begin preparations.
喂，快去準備
-For an investigation. -Huh?
-準備搜索 -什麼？
You're up to something, aren't you?
你在打什麼算盤吧？
Since you insist, let's see what you can do.
既然你都講到這個份上了 就讓我見識一下你的實力吧
If anything happens, we'll send in troops at once.
若有狀況，我會立刻讓部隊攻進去
Am I clear?
聽懂了嗎？
Yes.
聽懂了
Is it like scrambled eggs?
是像炒蛋嗎？
Huh?
什麼？
You once likened souls to eggs.
你曾將靈魂比喻為蛋
If two souls are blended together,
靈魂混合的狀態
what kind of egg would that be like?
若用蛋來比喻是什麼樣的蛋？
For example,
例如說
a scrambled egg is entirely different from a sunny side up.
炒蛋和荷包蛋，這兩種蛋完全不同啊
Listen.
我說啊
I didn't use an egg to illustrate a soul
我不是為了讓你挑人語病 玩文字遊戲
so you could jump on my words and play with them.
才把靈魂比喻成蛋的
Is that so?
是嗎？
I thought it was quite a clever metaphor.
老夫當時覺得這是很巧妙的比喻呢
Nothing has as many properties as an egg.
沒有其他東西像蛋一樣 擁有如此多樣的性質
Consider, for example, its coagulation temperature.
好比說這種加熱凝固的性質
The whites and yolks coagulate at different temperatures.
蛋白和蛋黃的凝固溫度就不同
It can be whipped, used as a moisturizer, and serve as an adhesive.
發泡、保濕、黏性
What's interesting is its emulsifying ability.
最有趣的是乳化
Despite water and oil being natural opposites,
就算是水和油 這種原本互不相容的物質
eggs can blend them together nicely, under the right conditions.
只要達到一定條件，也可均勻混合
Like so.
就像這樣
Well…
這個嘛…
True, why did I liken souls to eggs?
確實如此 為何我會用蛋來比喻靈魂？
Laios, fetch me the bread over there.
萊歐斯，把那裡的麵包拿來
It's done!
完成了！
SOUL EGGS BENEDICT
（靈魂班尼迪克蛋）
How do you eat this?
這要怎麼吃啊？
Use a fork and knife.
用刀子和叉子
Scoop up the yolk and sauce with the bread.
食用時以麵包撈取蛋黃和醬汁
Naturally, it's delicious.
理所當然地好吃
Izutsumi,
莞苞
would you stop glancing around at nothing?
你的視線不要一直追著 什麼都沒有的地方跑啦
Or do you actually see something?
還是說你看到什麼了？
Not really.
沒有啊
I just thought I sensed a presence.
我只是有感應到一些氣息
What?
什麼？
Maybe what I'm seeing isn't a hallucination!
這該不會不是幻覺吧？
Huh?
啥？
Well, the other day when I had mana sickness,
之前經歷魔力暈時
I mentioned seeing and hearing things, right?
我不是跟你們說 我會看到幻覺和幻聽嗎？
It's been going on this whole time.
其實這狀況一直持續著
This whole time? Why didn't you tell us?
一直？你為何不講？
Because he'd be quick to think there's something wrong with my head.
因為他總是沒事就愛嚇我 說是我頭腦有病
Am I wrong, though?
你分明就有病
What are the hallucinations like?
是怎樣的幻覺？
I hear someone talking to me constantly.
經常有人對著我講話
At first, I couldn't make out the words.
一開始我聽不懂對方在講什麼
But over time, both its voice and form have become clearer.
但聲音和形體越來越清晰
I was scared, so I've been trying to ignore it, but…
雖然我因為害怕 所以一直裝作沒看到…
So you could hear me all along.
你果然一直都有聽到我的聲音嘛
What did it say just now?
他剛剛說了什麼？
It's upset because I've been ignoring him.
因為我無視他，他好像很生氣
Is it safe to talk with it?
跟他講話不會有問題嗎？
Does it feel evil?
感覺像惡靈嗎？
Yeah. If anything, I'd say so.
是啊，硬要說的話滿像的
Hey.
你好
How can I help you?
請問你找我有什麼事嗎？
What's it saying?
他說什麼？
It's upset I'm treating it like a fiend.
他很氣我把他當成惡靈
Also…
還有…
it's saying, "Aren't you grateful I saved you from the magician?"
他還說“你忘了我從魔術師手上 救了你的恩情嗎？”
Huh?
什麼？
I remember now!
是指那時候的事啊！
That did happen, didn't it?
這麼說來，好像有那麼一回事
Thank it for us.
幫我們謝謝他
It wants us to meet someone.
他說想介紹一個人給我們認識
What should we do?
怎麼辦？
This someone better not be a Grim Reaper.
不會是死神吧？
Well, we don't really have other options.
好吧，反正我們也沒別的選擇
Okay! Take us to this person!
好，那就帶我們去見那個人吧！
What?
什麼？
This place…
這個地方是…
Hey!
喂！
Watch out!
很危險喔！
A U-Unicorn!
獨角獸！
You guys, are you from outside by any chance?
你們該不會是從外地來的吧？
No, we were in the dungeon and…
不，我們是從迷宮…
This is a big deal!
這下不得了！
Come with me!
跟我來！
The monsters are so tame.
魔物居然如此溫馴
They're under orders not to hurt us.
因為魔物被命令不得傷害我們
But you outsiders are different.
但你們外地人就不同了
Always keep the village's things on you.
記得身上一定要帶著村裡的東西喔
Izutsumi, what's the matter?
莞苞，怎麼了？
Is it teleportation sickness?
是轉移暈嗎？
Maybe the fatigue's getting to her.
她可能是累了
Is that the Golden Castle?
那是黃金城堡嗎？
Yup.
沒錯
We were brought here by some ghosts.
是幽靈介紹我們來這裡的
Are they residents here?
他們是這裡的居民嗎？
They are.
對…
But you can hear all about it from the person you're about to meet.
詳情你就問待會要去見的人吧
I don't really understand why you guys were chosen either.
我也不知道為何會選上你們
"Chosen"?
“選上”？
Here we are.
到了
Sit tight for a bit.
你們等一下
The master's gone to worship.
老爺去祈禱了
-It's them. -What?
-就是他們 -什麼？
These guys?
那些人嗎？
Seems you were out of luck a bit.
你們來得真不巧
Make yourselves comfortable in the village until the master comes home.
在這裡的主人回來之前 你們就在村中休息一下吧
It seems like everyone's dying to look after you guys, anyway.
大家似乎也很想跟你們相處
What should we show you?
該帶他們去哪裡逛逛好呢？
There isn't much to see in this village.
畢竟我們村莊沒什麼好看的
Are they all residents of the Golden Castle?
他們都是黃金城堡的居民嗎？
I don't see any elderly people around.
看起來沒有老人呢
I want to see where the monsters are kept.
我想看飼養魔物的地方
I'd like to check out the fields we passed on our way here.
老夫想去看剛才經過的田
What? That's what you're interested in?
什麼？去那種地方就行了嗎？
Sure, we can take you there.
沒問題，可以帶你們去
-Hurray!
-太棒了！
I'll wait here.
我在這裡等你們
We can't leave Izutsumi alone anyway.
畢竟不能把莞苞丟在這邊
I'll stay too.
我也要留下
A-A Minotaur…
居然是米諾陶洛斯…
Female?!
還是母的？
They're our milk cows.
牠們是乳牛的替代品
Why use monsters as livestock?
為何將魔物當成家畜養呢？
Huh?
什麼？
Well, regular livestock was hard to acquire.
因為一般的家畜很難取得啊
This is a fine, well-tended field.
有受到悉心照料，是相當棒的田呢
Do the villagers consume all the produce?
這些農作物只有村裡的人在吃？
Actually, there's a lot of waste.
的確有許多都報廢了
But without fields, there's nothing for us to do.
但若沒了田，我們也沒事做
We're maintaining them to replicate our lifestyle from above ground.
所以就算是形式上也好 我們維持和地表相同的生活
Oh!
居然是這樣！
Izutsumi, are you okay?
莞苞，你沒事吧？
At least she doesn't seem to be unwell.
她看起來似乎不是身體不適
Um, could we get a moment of your time?
那個，可以打擾一下嗎？
Dresses?
洋裝？
Exactly!
對！
We make clothes!
是我們做的衣服！
We usually take turns dressing up,
我們經常會換著穿
but it's become monotonous with the same members.
但因為都是同一批人，實在很無趣
I'd be happy to help.
如果你們不嫌棄我，當然可以
Which one should we try?
要選哪件好呢？
I think we should go with red.
果然還是紅色吧
Sorry,
抱歉
they might seem old-fashioned to you.
你可能會覺得衣服的款式很過時
I wouldn't say that.
不會啦
This isn't quite what I was expecting.
感覺跟我原本想的不太一樣
I suppose being isolated from the outside for a millennium would alter fashion too.
畢竟與外界隔絕了一千年 流行當然也會有所不同
Try these next!
接下來戴上這個吧！
That's good!
真好喝！
I'm pretty particular about my drinks,
我對酒還滿挑剔的
but this is pretty decent.
但這還挺不賴的嘛
I'm honored.
我深感榮幸
I serve it to orcs sometimes,
我有時會讓半獸人喝
and the latest batches have been quite popular.
最近這一批評價特別高呢
It's really nice.
真讚啊
Do you happen to make wine as well?
你該不會也有釀葡萄酒吧？
I've actually just begun recently.
其實我最近才開始釀
But compared to the ale that I've been brewing for 400 years,
但和釀了400年的艾爾啤酒比起來
it's been a bit tricky.
還是差強人意
Four hundred years?
400年？
That's a long-standing brewery!
還真是歷史悠久的釀酒廠啊！
What generation are you?
你是第幾代啊？
I began when I was 600 years old, so I'm the first generation.
是在600歲時開始釀酒的 我就是第一代喔
I see.
這樣啊
They let me milk a Minotaur!
他們讓我擠米諾陶洛斯的奶耶！
That's cool.
那真棒啊
Keep it to yourself.
你自己知道就好
This is incredible!
太厲害了！
They've completely succeeded in cultivating monsters here!
他們在此成功養殖魔物！
Just look at that vast Dryad farm!
你看那片廣大的樹精農場！
They've got four nipples, just like a cow!
牠們和牛一樣有四個乳頭！
This is making me feel sick.
感覺醉得好不舒服
Anyway, it was an amazing experience.
天啊，是一段珍貴的體驗呢
Milking a--
竟能那樣擠奶…
Speaking of which, where are Marcille and Izutsumi?
話說回來，瑪露希爾和莞苞人呢？
How did that bring them to mind?
你這是什麼樣的聯想啊？
S-Sorry for the wait.
抱歉讓你們久等了
What's up with your outfits? You're having too much fun!
你怎麼穿成這樣？玩得太開心了吧！
It's not like that!
不是你想的那樣！
They wanted us to, and we couldn't say no.
是因為她們拜託我，我才不得不穿
I did choose the tamest one, you know.
我選的已經是看起來最低調的了
NOT TAME
（毫不低調的）
Marcille, you…
瑪露希爾，那是…
W-What?
什麼啊？
Why is Izutsumi so attached to you?
為何莞苞這麼黏你？
That's your question?
你想問的是這個？
I wonder too!
我也不知道為何會這樣耶！
It's like she's regressed to infancy.
感覺她好像退化成幼兒了
Hmm!
是喔！
No!
討厭！
There are multiple barriers layered on top of each other here.
這裡被設下了多重且大量的結界
So maybe they're somehow interfering with something inside Izutsumi.
可能因此對莞苞有什麼影響吧
Because she's half-monster?
因為她有一半是魔物？
Yeah.
對
I've never encountered a barrier that suppresses aggression in monsters before.
但是我從未看過 能消除魔物攻擊性的結界
If only I could decipher this.
如果我能解讀就好了
But there are too many unfamiliar characters,
但有太多我沒看過的文字
I can't solve it overnight!
要我在一夕之間解開是不可能的
Everything I try to study is censored these days!
最近無論是什麼都會受到檢閱！
But this place is really amazing.
但這裡真的是個好地方
If it weren't for this situation, I'd have loved to remain here forever.
若不是處在這個情況下 我還真想一直待著
Me too.
我也是
Sorry for the wait.
不好意思讓各位久等了
Although modest, we've prepared a meal for you.
我們準備了一桌簡單的飯菜
Please follow me.
請跟我來
Welcome, everyone.
歡迎你們
I've been looking forward to meeting you.
我一直都期待能見到你們
My name is Yaad.
我的名字叫雅德
I'm the grandson of Delgal, whom you must be familiar with.
你們應該知道迪爾加路 我就是他的孫子
Delgal…
迪爾加路…
Please take a seat.
各位請坐
I'll share with you the long tale of why I've summoned you here.
我來講講請你們前來的原因 這件事說來話長
Serve them.
上菜吧
VEGETABLES IN SLIME ASPIC BEEF RIB STEAK
（蔬菜史萊姆凍 烤牛肋排）
BLADE FISH LOAF POTATO AND RABBIT SOUP
（馬鈴薯兔肉湯 刃魚糕）
Um, what kind of meat is this?
請問一下，這是什麼肉？
Right. As your group specifically requested,
是，因為我們有收到大家的要求
it's Minotaur meat.
所以用了米諾陶洛斯的肉
Do you regularly eat monsters too?
你們平常也會吃魔物嗎？
Some do, but we generally don't eat at all.
有些人會吃，但我們基本上不進食
Partly because our sense of taste has diminished,
一部分是因為我們的味覺已經鈍化
but in the first place, we don't experience hunger at all.
但歸根究柢，我們無法感受到食慾
That's the curse of immortality the lunatic magician has placed on us.
那便是狂亂魔術師 對我們所下的長生不老的詛咒
Why did the magician do such a thing?
為何魔術師要那麼做？
Who knows?
我也不知道
By the time I was old enough to understand things,
自從我有記憶以來
he was no longer in a state to hold proper conversations.
他就不是處在能夠正常對話的狀態
But don't concern yourselves about us.
不過不用顧慮我們
Please, enjoy your meal.
你們就盡情享用餐點吧
We might not feel any hunger, but it pleases us to watch others eat!
雖說沒有食慾 但看到他人進食，我們還是很開心
-I can't say I don't want to eat now!
-現在這氣氛不能說我不想吃！
My grandfather…
我的祖父…
blamed himself for turning the magician's focus on black magic.
似乎認為狂亂魔術師 會熱衷於黑魔法都是自己的責任
And he agonized over it for a long time.
因此長年來備受煎熬
Eventually, he headed to the surface seeking assistance.
最終他為了求助而前往地表
How is my grandfather known on the surface?
地表的人是怎麼說我祖父的呢？
As far as I've heard,
我聽說
he emerged suddenly from an underground graveyard near a village.
有一天他突然現身於村子的地下墓地
He named himself the king of a fallen kingdom,
說自己是亡國之王
and offered the entire realm to anyone who could defeat the lunatic magician.
並告訴大家他會將國家的一切 送給打倒狂亂魔術師的人
Then, he turned to dust.
之後便化為塵埃
Is that so?
這樣啊
At least there's some solace in knowing
至少祖父已經從痛苦中解放了
that he has been liberated from his suffering.
得知這點讓我感到欣慰
Many have left the village seeking to escape the curse.
有很多人為了逃離詛咒離開了村莊
But none have succeeded.
但從未有人成功
They've simply lost their flesh.
大家就只是失去了肉體
Without their bodies, they gradually lost their identities,
失去肉體後，漸漸會失去自我
transformed into fiends, and are unable to return here.
最終化為惡靈，再也無法回到這裡
You must've encountered some of them.
你們應該也有遇過幾次
-We have!
-的確有！
-We blasted them with holy water
-而且還對他們潑聖水
-and made sorbet out of it too!
-將他們做成了雪酪！
S-So,
所以說
what's the reason behind inviting us here?
你邀請我們來這裡的目的是？
The prophecy.
是因為預言
The prophecy?
預言？
That's right.
對
"There will come one bearing a winged sword,
“那個人帶著羽翼之劍
who will defeat the lunatic magician and free us."
將會打敗狂亂的魔術師，解放我們”
Winged?
羽翼？
Does that mean Kensuke?
是指劍助嗎？
It does have wings, but…
劍助確實有羽翼，但是…
Huh? It has a lion's face on it!
奇怪？怎麼是獅子的臉？
When did that happen?
什麼時候變成這樣的？
The Winged Lion is the guardian deity of this kingdom.
翼獅是這個國家的守護神
The lunatic magician has imprisoned it at the depths of the dungeon.
雖然被狂亂魔術師囚禁於迷宮底部
But even now, through dreams, it prophesies the future and guides us.
但牠透過夢境預言未來 至今仍引導著我們
My grandfather also left for the surface because of a prophecy.
祖父會前往地表的契機也是預言
Sir Laios,
萊歐斯閣下
the prophecy continues like this.
那個預言還有下文
"The bearer of the winged sword will defeat the lunatic magician,
“帶著羽翼之劍者 將會打敗狂亂的魔術師
and become the new king of this kingdom."
並成為這個國家的新王”
You've got the wrong person!
你找錯人了！
He only picked up this sword by chance!
這把劍是他碰巧撿到的！
It wasn't chance.
並非偶然
The fact that it's here now suggests it was predestined.
此刻劍會在這裡出現 代表一切早已注定
Sir Laios,
萊歐斯閣下
will you give us your word?
請你答應我好嗎？
That you will defeat the lunatic magician
說你會打倒狂亂魔術師
and liberate us.
並解放我們
I…
我…
Um…
那個…
Please let me think about it.
請讓我考慮一下
Just say no.
你直接拒絕啦
Why are you giving them false hope?
幹嘛給對方一線希望啊？
I can't just turn them down.
但也不能不加思索就拒絕吧
Kensuke,
劍助
when did you undergo your transformation?
你究竟是在何時變成這個樣子的？
It might have happened when the Dungeon Cleaners got to it.
感覺可能是 被迷宮清道夫吞噬的那時候
I was so nervous
難得的料理不知道是否因為太過緊張
that I couldn't really taste the food they prepared.
不管吃什麼都食不知味
You shameless bastard!
你這傢伙還好意思說！
How dare you make a request on our behalf!
什麼叫“大家的要求”啊？
In truth, it barely had any taste at all.
實際上那些料理幾乎都沒味道
They mentioned they don't need to eat.
他們說過自己不需要進食
That's why their cooking skills are lacking.
應是因為這樣才不太會烹調吧
I've been thinking.
老夫一直在想
They shouldn't need fields or dishes.
他們其實根本不需要田或餐具
So why do they have them?
但那些東西為何還在？
Why do they persist in cleaning and maintaining them for a millennium?
為何他們細心維護那些？ 長達一千年都保持良好狀態？
It must be because they depended on them
一定是因為有其必要吧
to stay sane and to keep on living.
為了讓自己保持理智，繼續活下去
Laios,
萊歐斯
I remember what you said to the orc chief.
老夫還記得你對半獸人族長說過的話
Huh?
什麼？
What did I say again?
我說了什麼啊？
Well, you should sleep on it for a night.
總之啊，你考慮一個晚上吧
Can I stay here too?
我也可以睡在這裡嗎？
Sleep in the room they prepared for you.
你去人家幫你準備的房間睡啦
I don't want to be alone!
我不想一個人睡啦！
Izutsumi is acting weird too.
莞苞也有點怪怪的
Scoot over.
擠過去一點…
Sleep on the floor!
你去睡地板啦！
His hands were cold.
他的手很冰冷
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻譯：周雨枏